and we crawl in, on your hands and knees into the spaceship, one at a time, and you worm your way up into your chair and plunk yourself down on your back. And the hatch is closed, and suddenly, what has been a lifetime of both dreams and denial is becoming real, something that I dreamed about, in fact, that I chose to do when I was nine years old, is now suddenly within not too many minutes of actually happening. In the astronaut business -- the shuttle is a very complicated vehicle; it's the most complicated flying machine ever built. And in the astronaut business, we have a saying, which is, there is no problem so bad that you can't make it worse. (Laughter) And so you're very conscious in the cockpit; you're thinking about all of the things that you might have to do, all the switches and all the wickets you have to go through. And as the time gets closer and closer, this excitement is building. And then about three and a half minutes before launch, the huge nozzles on the back, like the size of big church bells, swing back and forth and the mass of them is such that it sways the whole vehicle, like the vehicle is alive underneath you, like an elephant getting up off its knees or something. And then about 30 seconds before launch, the vehicle is completely alive -- it is ready to go -- the APUs are running, the computers are all self-contained, it's ready to leave the planet. And 15 seconds before launch, this happens: (Video) Voice: 12, 11, 10, nine, eight, seven, six -- (Space shuttle preparing for takeoff) -- start, two, one, booster ignition, and liftoff of the space shuttle Discovery, returning to the space station, paving the way ... (Space shuttle taking off) Chris Hadfield: It is incredibly powerful to be on board one of these things. You are in the grip of something that is vastly more powerful than yourself. It's shaking you so hard you can't focus on the instruments in front of you. It's like you're in the jaws of some enormous dog and there's a foot in the small of your back pushing you into space, accelerating wildly straight up, shouldering your way through the air, and you're in a very complex place -- paying attention, watching the vehicle go through each one of its wickets with a steadily increasing smile on your face. After two minutes, those solid rockets explode off and then you just have the liquid engines, the hydrogen and oxygen, and it's as if you're in a dragster with your foot to the floor and accelerating like you've never accelerated. You get lighter and lighter, the force gets on us heavier and heavier. It feels like someone's pouring cement on you or something. Until finally, after about eight minutes and 40 seconds or so, we are finally at exactly the right altitude, exactly the right speed, the right direction, the engine shut off, and we're weightless. And we're alive. It's an amazing experience. But why would we take that risk? Why would you do something that dangerous? In my case the answer is fairly straightforward. I was inspired as a youngster that this was what I wanted to do. I watched the first people walk on the moon and to me, it was just an obvious thing -- I want to somehow turn myself into that. But the real question is, how do you deal with the danger of it and the fear that comes from it? How do you deal with fear versus danger? And having the goal in mind, thinking about where it might lead, directed me to a life of looking at all of the small details to allow this to become possible, to be able to launch and go help build a space station where you are on board a million-pound creation that's going around the world at five miles a second, eight kilometers a second, around the world 16 times a day, with experiments on board that are teaching us what the substance of the universe is made of and running 200 experiments inside. But maybe even more importantly, allowing us to see the world in a way that is impossible through any other means, to be able to look down and have -- if your jaw could drop, it would -- the jaw-dropping gorgeousness of the turning orb like a self-propelled art gallery of fantastic, constantly changing beauty that is the world itself. And you see, because of the speed, a sunrise or a sunset every 45 minutes for half a year. And the most magnificent part of all that is to go outside on a spacewalk. You are in a one-person spaceship that is your spacesuit, and you're going through space with the world. It's an entirely different perspective, you're not looking up at the universe, you and the Earth are going through the universe together. And you're holding on with one hand, looking at the world turn beside you. It's roaring silently with color and texture as it pours by mesmerizingly next to you. And if you can tear your eyes away from that and you look under your arm down at the rest of everything, it's unfathomable blackness, with a texture you feel like you could stick your hand into. and you are holding on with one hand, one link to the other seven billion people. And I was outside on my first spacewalk when my left eye went blind, and I didn't know why. Suddenly my left eye slammed shut in great pain and I couldn't figure out why my eye wasn't working. I was thinking, what do I do next? I thought, well maybe that's why we have two eyes, so I kept working. But unfortunately, without gravity, tears don't fall. So you just get a bigger and bigger ball of whatever that is mixed with your tears on your eye until eventually, the ball becomes so big that the surface tension takes it across the bridge of your nose like a tiny little waterfall and goes "goosh" into your other eye, and now I was completely blind outside the spaceship. So what's the scariest thing you've ever done? (Laughter) Maybe it's spiders. A lot of people are afraid of spiders. I think you should be afraid of spiders -- spiders are creepy and they've got long, hairy legs, and spiders like this one, the brown recluse -- it's horrible. If a brown recluse bites you, you end with one of these horrible, big necrotic things on your leg and there might be one right now sitting on the chair behind you, in fact. And how do you know? And so a spider lands on you, and you go through this great, spasmy attack because spiders are scary. But then you could say, well is there a brown recluse sitting on the chair beside me or not? I don't know. Are there brown recluses here? So if you actually do the research, you find out that in the world there are about 50,000 different types of spiders, and there are about two dozen that are venomous out of 50,000. And if you're in Canada, because of the cold winters here in B.C., there's about 720, 730 different types of spiders and there's one -- one -- that is venomous, and its venom isn't even fatal, it's just kind of like a nasty sting. And that spider -- not only that, but that spider has beautiful markings on it, it's like "I'm dangerous. I got a big radiation symbol on my back, it's the black widow." So, if you're even slightly careful you can avoid running into the one spider -- and it lives close the ground, you're walking along, you are never going to go through a spider web where a black widow bites you. Spider webs like this, it doesn't build those, it builds them down in the corners. And its a black widow because the female spider eats the male; it doesn't care about you. So in fact, the next time you walk into a spiderweb, you don't need to panic and go with your caveman reaction. The danger is entirely different than the fear. How do you get around it, though? How do you change your behavior? Well, next time you see a spiderweb, have a good look, make sure it's not a black widow spider, and then walk into it. And then you see another spiderweb and walk into that one. It's just a little bit of fluffy stuff. It's not a big deal. And the spider that may come out is no more threat to you than a lady bug or a butterfly. And then I guarantee you if you walk through 100 spiderwebs you will have changed your fundamental human behavior, your caveman reaction, and you will now be able to walk in the park in the morning and not worry about that spiderweb -- or into your grandma's attic or whatever, into your own basement. And you can apply this to anything. If you're outside on a spacewalk and you're blinded, your natural reaction would be to panic, I think. It would make you nervous and worried. But we had considered all the venom, and we had practiced with a whole variety of different spiderwebs. We knew everything there is to know about the spacesuit and we trained underwater thousands of times. And we don't just practice things going right, we practice things going wrong all the time, so that you are constantly walking through those spiderwebs. And not just underwater, but also in virtual reality labs with the helmet and the gloves so you feel like it's realistic. So when you finally actually get outside on a spacewalk, it feels much different than it would if you just went out first time. And even if you're blinded, your natural, panicky reaction doesn't happen. Instead you kind of look around and go, "Okay, I can't see, but I can hear, I can talk, Scott Parazynski is out here with me. He could come over and help me." We actually practiced incapacitated crew rescue, so he could float me like a blimp and stuff me into the airlock if he had to. I could find my own way back. It's not nearly as big a deal. And actually, if you keep on crying for a while, whatever that gunk was that's in your eye starts to dilute and you can start to see again, and Houston, if you negotiate with them, they will let you then keep working. We finished everything on the spacewalk and when we came back inside, Jeff got some cotton batting and took the crusty stuff around my eyes, and it turned out it was just the anti-fog, sort of a mixture of oil and soap, that got in my eye. And now we use Johnson's No More Tears, which we probably should've been using right from the very beginning. (Laughter) But the key to that is by looking at the difference between perceived danger and actual danger, where is the real risk? What is the real thing that you should be afraid of? Not just a generic fear of bad things happening. You can fundamentally change your reaction to things so that it allows you to go places and see things and do things that otherwise would be completely denied to you ... where you could see the hardpan south of the Sahara, or you can see New York City in a way that is almost dreamlike, or the unconscious gingham of Eastern Europe fields or the Great Lakes as a collection of small puddles. You can see the fault lines of San Francisco and the way the water pours out under the bridge, just entirely different than any other way that you could have if you had not found a way to conquer your fear. You see a beauty that otherwise never would have happened. It's time to come home at the end. This is our spaceship, the Soyuz, that little one. Three of us climb in, and then this spaceship detaches from the station and falls into the atmosphere. These two parts here actually melt, we jettison them and they burn up in the atmosphere. The only part that survives is the little bullet that we're riding in, and it falls into the atmosphere, and in essence you are riding a meteorite home, and riding meteorites is scary, and it ought to be. But instead of riding into the atmosphere just screaming, like you would if suddenly you found yourself riding a meteorite back to Earth -- (Laughter) -- instead, 20 years previously we had started studying Russian, and then once you learn Russian, then we learned orbital mechanics in Russian, and then we learned vehicle control theory, and then we got into the simulator and practiced over and over and over again. And in fact, you can fly this meteorite and steer it and land in about a 15-kilometer circle anywhere on the Earth. So in fact, when our crew was coming back into the atmosphere inside the Soyuz, we weren't screaming, we were laughing; it was fun. And when the great big parachute opened, we knew that if it didn't open there's a second parachute, and it runs on a nice little clockwork mechanism. So we came back, we came thundering back to Earth and this is what it looked like to land in a Soyuz, in Kazakhstan. (Video) Reporter: And you can see one of those search and recovery helicopters, once again that helicopter part of dozen such Russian Mi-8 helicopters. Touchdown -- 3:14 and 48 seconds, a.m. Central Time. CH: And you roll to a stop as if someone threw your spaceship at the ground and it tumbles end over end, but you're ready for it you're in a custom-built seat, you know how the shock absorber works. And then eventually the Russians reach in, drag you out, plunk you into a chair, and you can now look back at what was an incredible experience. You have taken the dreams of that nine-year-old boy, which were impossible and dauntingly scary, dauntingly terrifying, and put them into practice, and figured out a way to reprogram yourself, to change your primal fear so that it allowed you to come back with a set of experiences and a level of inspiration for other people that never could have been possible otherwise. Just to finish, they asked me to play that guitar. I know this song, and it's really a tribute to the genius of David Bowie himself, but it's also, I think, a reflection of the fact that we are not machines exploring the universe, we are people, and we're taking that ability to adapt and that ability to understand and the ability to take our own self-perception into a new place. (Music)
reptando con manos y rodillas, entramos a la nave, de a uno a la vez, abriéndonos camino, reptando, hasta desplomarnos en los asientos, de espalda. Se cierra la escotilla y, de repente, toda una vida de sueños y negaciones se vuelve real, algo que soñé, de hecho, algo que elegí a los 9 años, de pronto ahora está a unos minutos de ocurrir de verdad. En el mundo de los astronautas, el transbordador es un vehículo muy complicado; es la máquina voladora más complicada de la historia. Y en astronáutica tenemos un dicho, que es: "Ningún problema es tan malo que no pueda ser peor". (Risas) Por eso uno está muy consciente en la cabina; uno piensa todas estas cosas que puede tener que hacer, todos los interruptores y ventanillas a atender. Y conforme se acerca el momento, la emoción se agiganta. Y unos 3 minutos y medio antes del lanzamiento, las enormes toberas de la parte posterior, del tamaño de grandes campanas, se bambolean y su masa es tal que hacen balancear a todo el vehículo, como si el vehículo estuviese vivo debajo de uno, como si un elefante de rodillas se levantase o algo así. Y luego unos 30 segundos antes del lanzamiento el vehículo está completamente vivo -- listo para salir -- las APUs están funcionando, las computadoras autocontenidas, listas para dejar el planeta. Y 15 segundos antes del lanzamiento, ocurre esto: (Video) Voz: 12, 11, 10, 9, 8, 7, 6... (Transbordador preparado para el despegue) ... inicio, 2, 1, ignición de propulsor, y despegue del transbordador espacial Discovery, de vuelta a la Estación Espacial, allanando el camino... (Transbordador despegando) Chris Hadfield: Es increíblemente poderoso estar a bordo una de estas cosas. Uno está en algo mucho más poderoso que sí mismo. Uno tiembla tanto que no se puede concentrar en los instrumentos que tiene en frente. Es como si uno estuviera en las fauces de un perro enorme y como si un pie en la parte baja de la espalda nos empujara al espacio, acelerando violentamente hacia arriba, catapultándonos por el aire, y uno está en un lugar muy complejo... prestando atención, viendo el vehículo pasar por cada una de sus etapas con una sonrisa cada vez mayor en la cara. Luego de dos minutos, esos cohetes sólidos se disparan y luego están los motores líquidos, el hidrógeno y el oxígeno, y es como si uno estuviese en un auto con el pie en el suelo, acelerando como si nunca hubiera acelerado. Uno se vuelve más y más liviano, la fuerza contra uno es cada vez más fuerte. Es como si alguien estuviese vertiendo cemento sobre uno. Hasta que por fin, después de cerca de 8 minutos y 40 segundos más o menos, por fin estamos exactamente a la altura correcta, exactamente la velocidad adecuada, la dirección correcta, el motor apagado, y estamos sin peso. Y estamos vivos. Es una experiencia increíble. Pero ¿por qué asumimos ese riesgo? ¿Por qué hacer algo tan peligroso? En mi caso la respuesta es bastante sencilla. Desde joven sentí la inspiración de que era lo que quería hacer. Vi a las primeras personas caminar en la luna y, para mí, fue algo obvio; quiero de algún modo participar en eso. Pero la verdadera pregunta es: ¿cómo lidiar con ese peligro y con el miedo que conlleva? ¿Cómo lidiar con el miedo versus el peligro? Y tener el objetivo en mente, pensando a dónde podría conducir, me llevó a una vida de atención a los pequeños detalles que permitieran hacer esto posible, a poder lanzar y ayudar a construir una estación espacial donde uno está a bordo de una creación de 45 toneladas que va por el mundo a 5 millas por segundo, 8 kilómetros por segundo, que da la vuelta al mundo 16 veces al día, con experimentos a bordo que nos están enseñando cuál es la sustancia que compone el universo y haciendo 200 experimentos dentro. Pero tal vez más importante aún, es que nos permite ver el mundo de una manera imposible por cualquier otro medio, poder mirar hacia abajo y si la mandíbula pudiera caerse lo haría, la magnificencia asombrosa del orbe que gira debajo como una galería de arte autopropulsada, de una belleza fantástica en cambio constante que es el mundo en sí. Y uno ve, dada la velocidad, un amanecer o un atardecer cada 45 minutos durante medio año. Y la parte más hermosa de todo eso es salir a dar una caminata espacial. Uno está en una nave espacial unipersonal que es el traje espacial, y va por el espacio junto con el mundo. Es una perspectiva totalmente diferente, uno no está mirando hacia el universo. La Tierra y uno juntos por el universo. Y uno sostenido con una mano, mira al mundo a su lado. Un silencio ensordecedor con color y textura conforme pasa cautivante al lado de uno. Si uno pudiera despegar los ojos de allí y mirar bajo el brazo hacia abajo todo lo demás, hay una negrura insondable, una textura de un espesor que uno siente que podría atravesar y sostener con una mano un vínculo con otros 7000 millones de personas. Y yo estaba fuera en mi primera caminata espacial cuando perdí la visión de mi ojo izquierdo, y yo no sabía por qué. De repente, mi ojo izquierdo se cerró de golpe con un gran dolor y yo no podía entender por qué mi ojo no estaba funcionando. Pensaba: ¿y ahora qué hago? Pensé, bueno, quizá por eso tenemos dos ojos, y seguí trabajando. Pero, por desgracia, sin gravedad las lágrimas no caen. Uno acaba teniendo una bola cada vez más grande de lo que sea mezclada con las lágrimas del ojo hasta que finalmente la bola es tan grande que la tensión superficial la lleva por el puente de la nariz como una diminuta cascada que pasa al otro ojo y ahora estaba completamente ciego fuera de la nave espacial. ¿Qué es lo más aterrador para Uds.? (Risas) Quizá las arañas. Mucha gente le teme a las arañas. Creo que deberían tener miedo a las arañas; las arañas son espeluznantes y tienen patas largas y peludas, y arañas como ésta, la reclusa marrón, es horrible. Si te pica una reclusa marrón terminas con uno de estas grandes necrosis en la pierna y podría haber una ahora en la silla detrás de Uds., de hecho. ¿Cómo saberlo? Una araña cae sobre Uds., y les da un gran ataque espasmódico porque las arañas son aterradoras. Pero entonces Uds. podrían decir, bueno ¿hay una reclusa marrón en la silla que está a mi lado o no? No lo sé. ¿Hay reclusas marrones aquí? Si investigan, descubrirán que en el mundo hay unos 50 000 tipos diferentes de arañas, y hay unas dos docenas que son venenosas de las 50 000. Y si están en Canadá, debido a los crudos inviernos aquí en la C.B., hay unos 720, 730 tipos diferentes de arañas y hay una -- una -- que es venenosa, y su veneno ni siquiera es mortal, es solo una picadura desagradable. Y esa araña -- no solo esa -- pero esa tiene marcas hermosas, dice: "Soy peligrosa, tengo símbolo de radiación"; es la viuda negra. Si uno incluso tiene un poco de cuidado puede evitar encontrarse con la araña -- vive cerca del suelo -- si uno va caminando, nunca atravesará una telaraña con una viuda negra que lo pique. No construyen telarañas como esta, las construye en las esquinas. Y es la viuda negra porque la hembra se come al macho; nosotros no les importamos. De hecho, la próxima vez que pisen una telaraña, no tienen que entrar en pánico y tener una reacción cavernícola. El peligro es totalmente diferente al miedo. ¿Cómo moverse entonces? ¿Cómo cambiar el comportamiento? Bueno, la próxima vez que vean una telaraña vean bien, asegúrese de que no es una viuda negra, y luego atraviésenla. Y luego ven otra telaraña y la atraviesan. Es solo algo esponjoso. No es gran cosa. Y la araña que puede aparecer no es una amenaza mayor que la de una mariquita o una mariposa. Les garantizo que si atraviesan 100 telas de araña habrán cambiado el comportamiento humano fundamental, la reacción cavernícola, y podrán caminar por el parque en la mañana sin preocuparse por esa telaraña, o por el ático de la abuela o lo que sea, o por su propio sótano. Y pueden aplicar esto a todo. Si uno está fuera en una caminata espacial y queda ciego, la reacción natural sería el pánico, pienso. Sería ponerse nervioso y preocuparse. Pero habíamos considerado todos los venenos, y practicado con una variedad de telarañas. Conocíamos todo lo que hay que saber sobre trajes espaciales y entrenamos bajo el agua miles de veces. Y no solo practicamos las cosas que van bien, practicamos cosas que salen mal todo el tiempo, así que estamos contantemente atravesando esas telarañas. Y no solo bajo el agua, sino también en laboratorios de realidad virtual con el casco y los guantes para sentir que es realista. Así que cuando por fin realmente salimos en una caminata espacial, se siente muy diferente que si se tratara de la primera vez. E incluso si uno está ciego no ocurre la reacción natural de pánico. En vez de eso, uno mira alrededor y dice: "Bueno, no puedo ver, pero puedo oír, puedo caminar, Scott Parazynski está aquí conmigo. Él podría venir en mi ayuda". En realidad practicamos rescate de tripulación incapacitada, así que podría llevarme como un dirigible y meterme en la esclusa de aire si tuviera que hacerlo. Podría abrirme mi propio camino de regreso. No es algo tan grave. Y, de hecho, si uno sigue lagrimeando durante un tiempo, cualquier basura del ojo empieza a diluirse y uno empieza a ver otra vez, y Houston, si uno negocia con ellos, ellos le permiten a uno seguir trabajando. Terminamos toda la caminata espacial y cuando regresamos adentro, Jeff con un cotonete quitó la basura de mis ojos, y resultó que era solo el antiniebla, una mezcla de aceite y jabón, que me entró en el ojo. Y ahora usamos No más lágrimas, de Johnson's que probablemente deberíamos haber usado desde el principio. (Risas) Pero la clave de eso es al mirar la diferencia entre el peligro percibido y el peligro real ¿cuál es el riesgo real? ¿Cuál es la cosa real a la que uno debe tener miedo? No un miedo genérico a que ocurran cosas malas. Uno puede cambiar de manera fundamental su reacción a las cosas de manera de poder llegar a lugares y ver cosas y hacer cosas que de otro modo nos estarían completamente negadas... podía ver el sur del Sahara, o la ciudad de Nueva York de una manera de ensueño, o la guinga inconsciente de los campos de Europa del Este o los Grandes Lagos como un conjunto de pequeños charcos. Uno puede ver la falla de San Francisco o la forma en que el agua pasa debajo del puente totalmente diferente de la forma que lo habría hecho de no haber encontrado la manera de conquistar sus miedos. Uno ve una belleza que de otro modo nunca habría visto. Es hora de volver a casa al final. Esta es nuestra nave, la pequeña Soyuz. Subimos tres tripulantes, y luego esta nave se separa de la estación y cae a la atmósfera. Estas dos partes se derriten, se funden y se queman en la atmósfera. La única parte que sobrevive es la pequeña bala en la que estamos montados, y cae a la atmósfera, y, básicamente, estamos montando un meteorito de regreso a casa, y montar meteoritos es aterrador, y así debe ser. Pero en vez de entrar a la atmósfera gritando como uno lo haría si de repente se encontrara montando un meteorito de regreso a la Tierra (Risas) en vez de eso, 20 años antes empezamos a estudiar ruso, y cuando aprendimos ruso, aprendimos mecánica orbital en ruso, y luego aprendimos teoría de control del vehículo, y luego entramos al simulador y practicamos una y otra y otra vez. Y, de hecho, se puede volar este meteorito y dirigirlo a la Tierra en un círculo de 15 kilómetros, a cualquier lugar de la Tierra. Por eso, cuando nuestra tripulación regresa a la atmósfera en la Soyuz, no gritamos, sino que reímos; fue divertido. Y cuando se abrió el gran paracaídas, sabíamos que de no abrirse hay un segundo paracaídas, y funciona con un pequeño y buen mecanismo de relojería. Así que regresamos, volvimos como un trueno, a la Tierra y esta es la forma de aterrizar en una Soyuz, en Kazajstán. (Video) Periodista: Pueden ver uno de esos helicópteros de búsqueda y recuperación, una vez más, ese helicóptero es parte de una docena de helicópteros rusos Mi-8. Aterrizaje - 03:14 y 48 segundos, a.m. Hora del Centro. CH: Y uno rueda hasta detenerse como si alguien tirara la nave de uno al suelo y esta girase de punta a punta, pero uno está listo para eso en un asiento hecho a medida, uno sabe cómo funciona el amortiguador. Y entonces, finalmente, llegan los rusos, te sacan, te ponen en una silla, y ahora uno puede mirar hacia atrás a lo que fue una experiencia increíble. Uno ha llevado los sueños de ese niño de 9 años, que eran imposibles e intimidantemente aterradores, intimidantemente temerarios, y ponerlos en práctica, e imaginar una forma de volver a autoprogramarse para cambiar ese miedo ancestral para que le permita a uno regresar con un repertorio de experiencias y un nivel de inspiración para otras personas que nunca podrían haber sido posibles de otro modo. Para concluir, me pidieron que toque la guitarra. Conozco esta canción, y es en realidad un tributo al genio del propio David Bowie, pero es también, pienso, reflejo del hecho de que no somos máquinas que exploran el universo; somos personas, y estamos tomando esa capacidad de adaptación y esa capacidad de comprensión y la capacitad de llevar nuestra propia autopercepción a un nuevo lugar. (Música)